(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-26T23:06:44.689090",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.6-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
世界がこんな風になって、どれくらい経っただろう
I wonder how long it's been since the world ended up like this.
どこまでも続く荒野、木々や植物に侵され崩れた建物、砂漠に埋もれ傾く巨大なビル群
Wastelands stretching endlessly, crumbling buildings overtaken by trees and flora, massive skyscrapers tilting as they sink into the desert.
もうずっとずっと前に起きた災厄によって世界は滅びてしまった
The world was destroyed long, long ago by a terrible calamity.
そんな黄昏を迎えた世界で……あたしは失われた文明の遺物を探すことを生業としている
In this world facing its twilight... I make a living searching for relics of lost civilizations.
浄水器や通信器のような今でも使えるものから、使い道のわからない箱のようなもの、朽ちかけた布などなど……
Things still usable today like water purifiers and transceivers, mystery boxes of unknown purpose, decaying cloth, and so on...
そういったものを手に入れて旅人として日々を過ごしながら、ずっと探しているものがある
As I gather those items and live my days as a traveler, there is something I've been searching for all along.
それは遥か昔にこの世界から失われてしまった……「オンガク」というもの
It is something that was lost from this world long ago... something called "Music".
それが何かはわからない
I don't even know what it is.
どうして探そうとしているのかも……よくはわからない
And I don't really know why I'm trying to find it...
でも不思議とその響きに、惹かれるのだ
Yet strangely, I am drawn to its sound.
だからあたしは世界を旅している
That's why I travel the world.
答えを探して、彷徨っている
Wandering in search of answers.
「オンガク」を見つけるために
To find "Music".
さ、今日もがんばっていくかー
Well, time to do my best today too.
いくせんの
Thousands of
はかない鼓動を 惜しまずに
fleeting heartbeats, without holding back,
流れる時を追い越して
overtaking the flowing time,
駆け抜ける世界……
running through this world...
いくつもの名前と
With so many names,
いくつもの姿を
and so many different forms,
使い分けて うまく生きているけど
I juggle them to get by just fine, but...
胸の奥 痛いよ
Deep in my chest, it hurts,
音立てて 軋むよ
squeaking and creaking loudly.
きっと 心 生命 ここにあるから
That's surely because my heart and life are right here.
.exe あたらしい あしたへ
.exe Toward a new tomorrow,
.exe 今 漕ぎ出す
.exe I set sail now.
.exe 運命の波間に さらわれたくはない！！
.exe I don't want to be swept away in the waves of fate!!
いくせんの
Thousands of
はかない鼓動を 惜しまずに
fleeting heartbeats, without holding back,
流れる時を追い越して
overtaking the flowing time,
駆け抜ける世界……
running through this world...
I pray among the stars
わたしはいつも祈ってる
I am always praying.
熱い思いをぶつけたら
If I pour out my passionate feelings,
奇跡さえ起こせるから！
I can even make miracles happen!
この景色 すべては
This entire scenery
寂しさで出来てる
is made out of loneliness.
願うだけで すぐにそばにいられた
Just by wishing, I could be right by your side back then.
あの頃の姿を
Seeking the image of those days,
追い求め さまよう
I wander around.
きっと 火花 言葉 ここにあるから
Surely, the sparks and words are right here.
.exe 懐かしい歌声
.exe A nostalgic singing voice,
.exe 今 聞こえる
.exe I can hear it now.
.exe 真空の中でも 受け取れるのはなぜ
.exe Why can I receive it even in a vacuum?
「通」じ合うこのよろこびを感じたい
I want to feel this joy of connecting with each other,
場所も時間も飛び越えて 分け合える世代
a generation sharing across space and time.
「信」じ合うことがすべてと悟ったよ
I realized that believing in each other is everything.
君をもう一度みつけたら 涙さえ輝くから
If I find you once again, even tears will shine.
いくせんの
Thousands of
はかない鼓動を 惜しまずに
fleeting heartbeats, without holding back,
流れる時を追い越して
overtaking the flowing time,
駆け抜ける世界……
running through this world...
「通」じ合うこのよろこびを感じたい
I want to feel this joy of connecting with each other,
場所も時間も飛び越えて 分け合える世代
a generation sharing across space and time.
「信」じ合うことが全てと悟ったよ
I realized that believing in each other is everything.
君をもう一度みつけたら 涙さえ輝くから
If I find you once again, even tears will shine.
もうこの世界には、人はあまり残っていない
There aren't many people left in this world anymore.
文明が崩壊して、インフラも何もかもなくなってしまったのだから、仕方ないことだと思う
Civilization collapsed and infrastructure was completely lost, so I guess it can't be helped.
（だけど旅をしていると、何かに引き寄せられるように誰かと出会うことがある）
(But as I travel, it feels like I'm drawn by something to meet someone new.)
（こんな風に）
(Just like this.)
こんにちは
Hello.
こんにちは。あなたは？
Hello. Who are you?
私はAZKi。この世界の地図を作りながら色々なところを調査する「開拓者」をしているわ。キミは？
I'm AZKi. I'm a "Pioneer" who surveys various places while mapping out this world. And you?
あたしは旅をしてるんだ。なくなってしまった大切なものを探すために
I'm on a journey. To search for something precious that was lost.
大切なもの？
Something precious?
うん…「音楽」を
Yeah... "Music."
ふーん
Hmm...
そう。この世界線ではそうなのね。でもあなたは覚えているはずだわ。
I see. So that's how it is in this worldline. But you should still remember it.
ん？
Huh?
記憶にはなくても、胸の奥の深いところに、いっしょに過ごした時間……気持ちをひとつにした瞬間を
Even if it's not in your memory, deep within your heart, the time we spent together... the moments our feelings aligned.
だってあなたにとってそれは……とても大事なものだったはずだから
Because to you, it was meant to be something very important...
あー 君が好きな服
Ah, the clothes you like,
濡れたままだけどね
even though they're still soaking wet.
こんな夜だから
Because on a night like this,
響かせて MUSIC
let the music resonate!
お気に入りの歌は
Your favorite song—
君は知らない
you don't even know it.
君だけ知らない
Only you don't know it.
感情論を君に投げつけて
Throwing emotional arguments at you,
傷ついたフリしてるけど
I pretend to be hurt, but...
完全論争 いつも言いたいくらい
Complete argument—I always want to say it so much,
もっと確かめてみる
I'll try to make sure even more.
全然論外 だけど涙出る
Completely out of the question, yet tears flow.
見ないでよ ひどい顔なの
Don't look at me, I look terrible right now.
単純じゃんって言われたくないよ
I don't want to hear "You're so simple."
もっと確かめてみて
Try to understand me more.
ねぇ 朝が来る前に
Hey, before morning comes,
抜け出してみた
I tried slipping away.
こんな夜だから
Because on a night like this,
鳴り止まない MUSIC
the music won't stop playing!
お気に入りの曲は
To my favorite song,
君は踊らない
you don't dance.
君だけ踊らない
Only you won't dance.
感情論で君を傷つけて
Hurting you with emotional arguments,
こんな人 嫌いになるでしょ
you'd hate someone like this, wouldn't you?
純情なんて呆れるくらいに
Being pure-hearted is almost absurdly
本当に似合わないけど
unfitting for me, but...
テンションジャンクション上げて知らんフリ
Cranking up the tension junction, pretending not to care,
困らせたいそんな気分よ
I just feel like flustering you.
単純じゃんって言われたくないよ
I don't want to hear "You're so simple."
きっと我がままだけど
I know I'm being selfish, but...
完全少女論 自分中心の 気分上々っといいじゃんこれで
Perfect Girls' Logic—self-centered, feeling great, isn't this fine as it is?
完全友情論 理解不能でしょ
Perfect Friendship Theory—it's incomprehensible, right?
ほんのちょっと手を伸ばして
Reaching out just a little bit,
割とぜんぜん気づかない
you don't seem to notice at all.
笑うよ 朝が来たら
I'll laugh when morning arrives.
大丈夫
It'll be okay,
だから
so...
感情論を君に投げつけて
Throwing emotional arguments at you,
演じてるフリしてるけど
I pretend to just be acting, but...
完全相思 いつも言いたいくらい
Complete mutual love—I always want to say it so much,
君は優しいけれど
even though you're so kind to me.
感情論を君に投げつけて
Throwing emotional arguments at you,
傷ついたフリしてるけど
I pretend to be hurt, but...
完全論争 いつも言いたいくらい
Complete argument—I always want to say it so much,
もっと確かめてみる
I'll try to make sure even more.
さっきのは……なんだったんだろう
What was that just now...?
たくさんの人たちと、その人たちが発する熱気に包まれて、あたしはすごくワクワクしてた
Surrounded by so many people and their heat, I was so excited.
何だがすごく懐かしい感じがした……
It felt strangely nostalgic...
ねぇねぇ、キミ、大丈夫？
Hey, are you okay?
え？
Huh?
なんか顔色がよくなかったからさ。あ、打ちはミオだよ。占い師をやってる。
You didn't look so good. Ah, I'm Mio. I'm a fortune teller.
ん、キミ、何かを探してるね。そう占いに出てる。
Hmm, you're looking for something, aren't you? That's what my fortune telling says.
わかるの？
You can tell?
うん、よかったら話してみて。何か力になれるかもしれないし。
Yeah. If you'd like, tell me about it. Maybe I can help you.
実は……
Actually...
なるほど……キミは「オンガク」を探してるんだね。
I see... So you're looking for "Music".
それならあそこに行ってみればいいんじゃない？
In that case, why not try going over there?
世界の果てにあるっていう、光の塔。
To the Tower of Light at the end of the world.
そこには”天使”が住んでて、やって来た人の願いを叶えてくれるんだって。だからそこに行ってお願いをすれば、キミの探し物も見つかるんじゃないかな？
An "angel" lives there, and they say she grants the wishes of those who visit. So if you go there and make a wish, you might find what you're looking for.
親切にありがとう。そこに行ってみることにするよ！
Thank you for your kindness. I'll go check it out!
どういたしまして。でもお礼なんていらないって。
You're welcome. But you don't need to thank me.
？
Huh?
だってうちは……キミのことが大好きだから！
Because... I love you so much!
ずっとずっと前からね！
Since way, way back!
遥か 遠く
Far, far away,
続く 果てなき道
the endless road continues.
それでも いつか
Even so, someday
たどり着くと 信じて
I believe I will reach the end.
たとえ 今は
Even if, right now,
辛く 厳しくても
it is painful and harsh,
小さな 笑顔
I will protect
守る すべて捧げて
that tiny smile, giving my all.
心 重なる
Our hearts overlap,
言葉より 強い絆
a bond stronger than words.
紡ぎ合っていく
We weave them together,
ひとつになる 鼓動で
becoming one with each beat.
記憶をたどる 追憶の旅
Tracing memories, a journey of recollection,
続けて……
continuing...
あらゆることを 受け止めるから
Because I will accept everything,
言葉はいらないの
we need no words.
それは 永遠に……
That is, forever...
いつも 近く
Always close,
そばで 見ていたけど
I was watching by your side,
気づかず いても
even if you didn't notice.
今は 強く感じる
Now, I feel it so strongly.
愛を 追いかけ
Chasing after love,
絆から 愛に変われば
if a bond transforms into love,
紡ぎ合っていく
we weave them together,
二人だけの 秘密
a secret for just the two of us.
思いをこめた 言葉の強さ
The strength of words filled with feelings...
見ている
Watching...
口にしたとき 覚悟していた
When I spoke those words, I was prepared.
未来を紡ぐために
To weave the future.
気づけばほら
Look, before I realized it,
心に宿るともしび
a light dwelling in my heart.
小さな光 寄り添い合えば
If small lights snuggle together,
その未来を指して
pointing toward that future,
青く広がる あれは渡る空
spreading blue, that sky we cross,
夜明ける
daybreak arrives.
もう言葉すら いらないから
Because we don't even need words anymore,
ただ 抱きしめていたい
I just want to hold you close.
時は 永遠に
Time, eternally...
（降り注ぐ雨のような歓声）
(Cheers like pouring rain)
（その中で、きらびやかな服を着たあたしは、幸せそうな笑顔で手を振っている）
(In the midst of it, dressed in glamorous clothes, I am waving with a happy smile)
（まるでもう一人のあたしのよう）
(As if it were another me)
（世界の果てにあるという光の塔）
(The Tower of Light said to be at the end of the world)
（「オンガク」を探すために、あたしはそこを目指すことに決めた）
(To search for "music", I decided to head for that place)
（何日かかるかわからないけど、幸いなことに時間はたくさんある）
(I don't know how many days it will take, but fortunately, I have plenty of time)
（ただ……）
(Just...)
お腹、空いた……
I'm hungry...
なんでわためを見てお腹を鳴らしてるの！？
Why did your stomach growl while looking at Watame?!
え、わからないけど、何かキミを見たら急に……
Eh, I don't know, but when I looked at you, suddenly...
わためは“非常食”じゃないよ〜！
Watame is not emergency food~!
見逃してくれたら、かわりにわためが歌うから〜！
If you let me go, Watame will sing for you instead~!
……ウタ？？
...Singing??
ウタって……なに？
What is... "singing"?
え、キミ、歌を知らないの？
Eh, you don't know what singing is?
よ〜し、じゃあわためが教えてあげるよ。
All right then, Watame will teach you.
歌っていうのはね〜
Singing is, you see...
滅びていくこのステラ
This collapsing stella,
絆を辿るストーリー
a story tracing our bonds.
受け継ぐ想いが
May the inherited feelings
生まれ変われますように
be reborn.
目の前現れた無表情は
The expressionless face that appeared before me,
誰にも懐を見せないまま
without showing its true heart to anyone.
事象が世界を歪ませて
The events distort the world,
光がただ眩しすぎたの
the light was simply too dazzling.
燦々と照りつける 荒野に残した足跡
Brilliantly shining down, footprints left in the wasteland.
与えられたのなら 守るものだけ
If given to me, I will only protect what matters.
滅びていくこのステラ
This collapsing stella,
叶うことがないとしても
even if it won't come true,
変えよう世界を 灯していく
let's change the world, lighting it up.
震える手がはじいた
A trembling hand flipped back
意味を持たない銃口
a meaningless muzzle.
輝く星の下
Under the shining stars,
わたしは今 息をする
I am breathing right now.
それなら あなたは騙したんだ
If so, you deceived me.
今ならすべて分かってしまう
Now, I understand everything.
名前を呼んでくれていても 私に受け入れられていなかった
Even if you called my name, I couldn't accept it.
消える日の前でただ 立ち尽くして煙る灰
Standing frozen before the day that vanishes, amid smoldering ashes,
命の理屈が今 答えを迫る
the logic of life now demands an answer.
滅びてゆくその中で 息を絶やした場所から 崩れた絆を 張り繋いで
Amidst this decay, stitching back together broken bonds from where breath ceased,
お願いどうかそばにいて 声が重心に求めた 終わりと始まりの時の中で
please stay by my side, as my voice called out from deep within, amidst the time of endings and beginnings.
瞳の奥に映った 壊れかけている心に持つ引き金に
Reflected deep in my eyes, on the trigger held by a breaking heart,
かけた指先が示す未来を祈るだろう
the finger placed upon it prays for the future it indicates.
滅びてゆくこのステラ 瞬きの数の傷 心がこのまま 途絶えてしまっても
This decaying stella, with wounds as many as blinks of an eye, even if my heart comes to an end like this,
私の生まれた理由を 手放さないでお願い 終わりと始まりの時の中で
please don't let go of the reason I was born, amidst the time of endings and beginnings.
私は確かにいるよ
I am truly right here.
何度でも確かめられるよ そこにあなたの存在と名前を あなたが生き抜いた世界は まだ私の中で息をする
I can confirm it again and again, your presence and name right there. The world you survived in still breathes inside me.
（光、光、光）
(Light, light, light...)
（その星のようなきらめきが――頭に焼きついて離れない）
(That starlike sparkle—it's burned into my mind and won't leave.)
（あの子がやっていたことはなんだったんだろう？）
(What was that girl doing?)
（「ウタ」だって言ってたけど……初めて聞く言葉だ）
(She called it "song"... but it's a word I've never heard before.)
（だけど「ウタ」は、あたしの心の深いところに確かに染み込んできた……）
(Yet that "song" definitely seeped deep into my heart...)
静かだなー……
It's so quiet...
（この世界は、ずっと静寂に包まれている）
(This world has been wrapped in silence for so long.)
（だけどさっきのあれは――「ウタ」は、そのどれとも違った）
(But what happened earlier—that "song"—was completely different from any of it.)
（あれは、なんなんだろう……）
(What was that...?)
（あと別れ際にくれたこの頭につける道具は……？ 遺物……？）
(And what is this tool for the head she gave me when we parted...? A relic...?)
（確か「ヘッドセット」って言ってた）
(I think she called it a "headset.")
（これを使えば……あたしも「ウタ」えるんだろうか）
(If I use this... can I "sing" too?)
forever has gone
today is infinity
and yesterday's dreams
today a faint memory
forever has gone
today is infinity
it's time to move on
forever has gone
two eyes in the face of billions of voices
I saw the flashing lights move further in the distance
(dream was not meant to be)
and outside these walls that I have created
The sound of stars colliding
Echoes in the distance
And dreams, they shatter
Let it break into a thousand pieces
Let the wind blow it all away
Dreams are fragile, but our hearts grow
Stronger from the memories...
Let it break into a thousand pieces
Let the wind blow it all away
Dreams are fragile, but our hearts grow
Stronger from the memories...
Renew... the light...
The dream...
Forever has gone
Today is infinity
And yesterday's dreams
Today a faint memory
Forever has gone
Today is infinity
It's time to move on
Forever has gone
Time to move on
It's time to move
And outside these walls that I have created
The sound of stars colliding
Echoes in the distance
And dreams, they shatter
Let it break into a thousand pieces
Let the wind blow it all away
Dreams are fragile, but our hearts grow
Stronger from the memories...
Let it break into a thousand pieces
Let the wind blow it all away
Dreams are fragile, but our hearts grow
Stronger from the memories...
Renew... the light... the dream...
Forever has gone
Today is infinity
And yesterday's dreams
Today a faint memory
Forever has gone
Today is infinity
It's time to move on
Forever has gone
Time to move on
It's time to move
（「ウタ」を知ってから、数日が経った。）
A few days have passed since I learned about "song."
（旅路は進み、ようやく光の塔がおぼろげながらに見えてくる）
As the journey continues, the Tower of Light finally comes faintly into view.
（だけど「オンガク」や「ウタ」について知っている人は、ほとんどいなかった）
However, hardly anyone knew anything about "music" or "song."
（もしかしたらあたしは、ないものねだりをしているだけなのかもしれない）
Perhaps I am simply asking for the impossible.
（でも……新しい出会いはあった）
But... I did have a new encounter.
Ciaoooo! I'm Raora Panthera!
あたし「絵描き」をやってるんだ！
I'm an artist!
きみを見たとき、ビビビッてきたの！「きみにはこれが似合いそう！」
When I saw you, I felt a spark! "This would look great on you!"
さらさらさらさら……っと
*Scribble, scribble...*
はい！プレゼント！
Here! A present!
これ……わたし？
Is this... me?
うん、『ステージ衣装』を着た、キミの絵！So cute……！
Yep! A picture of you in a "stage outfit"! So cute...!
ちょ、ちょっと私には可愛すぎない？
Wait, isn't this a bit too cute for me?
そんなことないよー！すっごくぴったり！
Not at all! It fits you perfectly!
そ、そうかな……？
R-Really...?
きみはこの『ステージ衣装』を着て……
Put on this "stage outfit" and...
Let's sing with me!!
YEAH~
The knacks of surviving in this world are being human and being right
Everyone keeps telling me to grow up fast And it is so tough, can't wrap my head around it
Your unfair rules Ego trip into a loop
We do belong nowhere in this world
Yet we are surviving Getting through anything Stay alive
Hated ones Naked hearts
Worthless games that never end
Found them in the darkness in the end
何が正しくて何が間違っているんだ
What is right and what is wrong?
僕はただここで生きてると叫びたいだけ
I just want to shout that I am living here
I heard voices calling out my true name
I will never give up or be swayed anymore
Nobody can stop me This is the way I am
I'll EXECUTE you, drop dead baby!! YEAH~
Everyone wanna choose the right path only
They would seek salvation in this closed world
Filthy hands and mind never set clean again though And it is so tough, can't wrap my head around it
Cannot turn the clock back Cannot take a turn back
We do belong nowhere in this world
Yet we are surviving Getting through anything Stay alive
Missing piece Warmth of hands
Joys and even stabbing pains
Found them in the darkness in the end
何が正しくて何が間違っているんだ
What is right and what is wrong?
誰だってここで生きてると叫んでいるのに
Even though everyone is shouting that they are living here
Facing what they really want to do,
They'll make it at the cost of everything
Nobody can stop me This is the way I am
I'll EXECUTE you, drop dead baby!! YEAH~
また失って、もう嫌になって
Losing again, sick and tired of it
それでも消えなくて
Yet still not disappearing
その心の名をなんと言うのだろう
What do you call that heart's name?
僕はここで今叫んでいるんだよ
I am shouting right here, right now
君だってここで同じように叫んでいるんだろう
You too are probably shouting here in the same way
I heard voices calling out my true name
I will never give up or be swayed anymore
Nobody can stop me This is the way I am
I'll EXECUTE you, drop dead baby!! YEAH~
So, this is the way I am YEAH~
色とりどりのかわいい『衣装』
(A colorful, cute "outfit"...)
それは不思議とぴったりと身体に馴染んでいた
(Strangely, it fit my body perfectly...)
『衣装』を身にまとい、『ヘッドセット』をつけて、『歌う』あたし
(Dressed in this "outfit," wearing a "headset," "singing"—that's me...)
あっちのあたしと、今のあたし、どっちが本物なんだろう
(That version of me, and the current me... I wonder which one is the real me?)
そういう時はね、難しいことは忘れて、パーッと楽しいことをするに限るかな？
At times like that, it's best to forget about complicated things and just do something fun!
クレープを焼いたりとか、アロマで癒されたりとか、
Whether it's baking crepes, relaxing with aromatherapy,
ベリーダンスを踊ったりとかして気持ちよくなれば、悩み事なんてどこかに飛んでいっちゃうものなんだよ。
or belly dancing to feel good, all your worries will just fly away!
そういうものなの？
Is that really how it works?
うん、そういうものかな～
Yep, that's pretty much it~
だって世の中の大部分のことは、それがどう見えるかなんていうのは見る人次第なんだから。
After all, how most things in this world look depends entirely on the person looking at them.
たとえばアキロゼのこの格好が、芸術的に見えるかセクシーに見えるかは、
For example, whether Akiroze's outfit here looks artistic or sexy...
あなたたち次第、みたいにね？うふふ。
...is completely up to you all, right? Hehehe.
え、あ... うん。
Eh, ah... yeah.
そうだ！せっかくこうして出会えたんだから、いっしょに踊ろっか？
I know! Since we managed to meet like this, shall we dance together?
あなたとアキロゼの二人で。
Just the two of us—you and Akiroze.
え、でもあたし、踊ったことなんてないんだけど...
Eh, but I've never danced before...
だいじょうぶ、だいじょうぶ。これはあなたのためだけに考えた、
It's okay, it's okay! This was made just for you—
『踊り子アキロゼの振り付け』だから。
—the choreography by "Dancer Akiroze."
ね？
Okay?
音のない大地に 恋の歌 響けば
When a song of love resounds across the silent land,
狂い出す歯車 止められぬ宿命（さだめ）が はじけた
the grinding gears turn, and an unstoppable fate bursts forth.
蘇る 今 いにしえより
Now revived from ancient times,
寂寥の恋 目覚めた
this lonely love awakens.
絆を求めて 炎はほとばしる
In search of a bond, the flames surge forth,
破壊と再生 気高き君の呪縛
destruction and rebirth—your noble curse.
透き通る魂 嘘もなく気高く
A translucent soul, noble and without lies,
原罪を抱えて 未熟な恋求む愚かさ
harboring original sin, the foolishness of seeking unripe love.
月明かり 今 ふたり照らす
Moonlight now illuminates the two of us,
束の間の時 重ねた
piling up brief moments in time.
絆の行方を 両手で抱きしめた
Holding tight to the future of our bond with both hands,
終わりと始まり 貴き君の記憶
an ending and a beginning—your precious memories.
絆を求めて
Seeking bonds,
炎は音を散らす
flames scatter the sound,
破壊と再生
destruction and rebirth,
気高き君の呪縛
the curse of your noble self.
絆の行方を
The whereabouts of our bond
両手で抱きしめた
I held tight with both hands.
終わりと始まり
An end and a beginning,
尊き君の記憶
your precious memories.
（どこか懐かしい誰かと出会う度に、頭に浮かぶ映像が鮮明になってくる）
(Every time I meet someone strangely familiar, the images in my head become clearer...)
（もう少しで……何かがわかりそうな気がした）
(I felt like... I was just on the verge of understanding something.)
それって、「ライブ」なんじゃないかな？
Isn't that... a "live concert"?
「ライブ」？
A "live concert"?
うん。そう。私、旅芸人だから噂で聞いたことがあるんだけど、「オンガク」があった頃にはよく開催されてたんだって。
Yeah. As a traveling performer, I've heard rumors that back when "music" existed, they were held all the time.
ふーん……
Hmm...
（そうだ、あたしは「ライブ」をやっていたんだ――）
(That's right... I used to perform "live concerts"--)
ねぇ、気になるなら今からここで私といっしょにやってみる？
Hey, if you're curious, wanna try doing one here with me right now?
え？
Eh?
ていうかやろうよ！ あなたとならやってみたい！ ――「ライブ」ってやつを！
Actually, let's do it! I want to try it with you! That thing called a "live concert"!
とおくで きこえる
Faintly heard in the distance,
わたしを 呼ぶ声
is a voice calling out to me.
あなたの 涙の
Your tears...
理由を知ってたはずなのに
I should have known the reason for them...
乾く前に 枯れる前に
Before they dry, before they wither,
全て 捧げようと
I resolved to offer everything
あなただけに
to you alone.
なにを求めるのか 誰を愛するのかさえ
Not knowing what I seek, or whom I love,
わからず
lost in uncertainty.
灰のように 朽ちていく心に
In my heart rotting away like ashes,
あなたのかけらだけは
only the fragments of you remain.
手探りでも かたちをなぞれば
Even in the dark, if I trace your shape,
長い眠りの中
within a long slumber,
あなたを 夢見るでしょう
I will surely dream of you.
ふたり 見慣れた あの日々を何度も
Reliving those familiar days together over and over,
夜明けは あなただけに
the dawn arrives for you alone.
空には もう 果てがないから
Because there are no longer any boundaries in the sky.
なにを求めたのか 遠い日のわたしに今
Asking my past self now what it was I sought,
問いかけ
I question myself,
砕かれ 色褪せ 落ちてく
shattered, faded, falling down.
あの かけらたちはどこへ――
Where have those fragments gone?...
手探りでも かたちをなぞった
Even in the dark, I traced its shape
長い夢の中で いま
Inside this long dream, now...
あなたと
With you...
また出会えた
We met once again.
ふたり願った
The two of us wished for this,
この時を最後まで
to hold this moment until the very end.
広がる 青い空が
As the blue sky spreads out,
あなたを いつでも見ているから
because it is always watching over you.
光の塔は もう目の前に迫っていた
The Tower of Light was already looming right before my eyes.
それにつれて 頭に浮かぶ映像は さらに鮮明になってきていた
As I drew closer, the images floating in my mind became even clearer.
まるで 夢から覚めるように
As if awakening from a dream...
まるで それが本物であるかのように
As if those images were real...
──「ライブ」をしていた場所が
—the place where we held our "live performance."
……着いた
...I've arrived.
ここが……光の塔
So this is... the Tower of Light.
塔っていうよりも、何かの舞台みたいにも見えるな
Rather than a tower, it looks more like some kind of stage.
似てる……気がする。あの、「ライブ」をやっていた場所に
It feels... familiar. Similar to that place where we held the "live."
いらっしゃい、ライオンさん
Welcome, Miss Lion.
キミが……願いを叶えてくれる「天使」？
Are you... the "angel" who will grant my wish?
うん。そう。キミが来るのを待ってたよ
Yes, that's right. I've been waiting for you to come.
この世界に……「オンガク」を取り戻すことができるキミを
Waiting for you, who can bring "music" back to this world.
「オンガク」を？ あたしが……？
"Music"? Me...?
そうだよ
That's right.
ここに来るまでにたくさんのものを受け取ったキミは、もう「オンガク」が何か分かってるんじゃないかな？
Having received so much on your way here, don't you already know what "music" is?
ほら、ボクといっしょに飛ぼう──
Come on, fly together with me—
囚われた絶望の淵で 私を抱きしめてください
Deep within the edge of trapped despair, please hold me close.
静寂に埋め尽くされ ひとり凍えている
Buried in complete silence, freezing all alone.
崩れ堕ちてゆく 楽園の果てで 忘れられた祈りが響いてる
At the end of a crumbling paradise, forgotten prayers resound.
支配する闇の中でも 褪せない愛よ 目覚めよ 永久に
Even within the governing darkness, unfading love, awaken for eternity!
無限に降り降る孤独を その指で染めてください
Please stain this endlessly falling solitude with your fingers.
叫ぶこの心が 悲しみを愛せるように
So that this screaming heart may come to love the sorrow.
まだ見ぬ あの光の景色へ
Toward that landscape of light yet unseen.
囚われた絶望の淵で 私を抱きしめてください
Deep within the edge of trapped despair, please hold me close.
乱れ咲く花より深く 優しく口づけてください
Deeper than profusely blooming flowers, please kiss me gently.
躊躇いの吐息さえも
Even hesitant sighs...
灯していく
Lighting up
虹の幻に
the phantom of the rainbow,
救済の鐘を
sound the bell of salvation,
その温もりすら 果てに届くまで
until even its warmth reaches the end.
ほとばしる 嵐の中でも
Even amidst the gushing storm,
やまない 愛を目覚めよ
awaken an unceasing love.
抗えぬ願いを
Receive these irresistible wishes
その手で迎えてください
into your hands, please.
出会えた喜びに
At the joy of having met,
震えている羽化の心で
with a heart emerging like a butterfly, trembling,
求めるあの残酷の彼方へ
toward that cruel beyond we seek.
壊されるたび 組み替えられる輪廻
Samsara rearranged each time it is broken.
こぼれちる涙が
When the spilled tears
キラキラと風に舞う頃
dance sparklingly in the wind,
絆を 痛みをくぐらせ
let the bonds pass through the pain,
永遠に消えないように
so that they never disappear for eternity.
無限に降る孤独を 私に預けてください
Please entrust to me the endless rain of solitude.
呼び合えた心が
Hearts that called out to each other
扉を放ち羽ばたく
release the door and spread their wings,
近づくあの始まりの空へ
drawing near to that sky of beginnings.
組み替えられる輪廻
Samsara being rearranged.
へー、この街の露店は品揃えがいいな
Huh, the street stalls in this town have a great selection.
他では見ない珍しいものがいっぱいある
There are tons of rare things you don't see elsewhere.
旅を続けてると、やっぱりどうしても装備品は必要になってくるからなあ……
When you're traveling, you definitely end up needing supplies and gear after all...
ちょっと覗いていこう
Let me take a quick look.
あ、これいいな。「ブランケットインクッション」
Ah, this looks nice. "Blanket-in-Cushion".
ブランケットなのに袋に収納すればクッションにもなるから、これがあればどこでもひと休みできて、旅のお供にぴったりかも
Even though it's a blanket, if you pack it into its bag, it turns into a cushion. With this, you can rest anywhere, making it perfect for traveling.
コンパクトなのにふかふかで、寝心地もよさそう
It's compact yet soft and fluffy, looks comfortable to sleep on too.
収納袋の絵もいい感じ
The illustration on the storage bag is cool too.
こっちは何だろう？
What's this one?
『SSRBミニウォレット』か……買い物したり、小物を収納するのに財布は必需品なんだよね
"SSRB Mini Wallet", huh... A wallet is an essential item when shopping or storing small things.
小銭もお札も入れられるっていうのも嬉しいな
It's great that it can hold both coins and bills.
今使ってるのも古くなってきたし、そろそろ買い替えてもいいかも
The one I'm using now is getting old, so maybe it's time to replace it.
お、この「ブレスレット」、かっこいい
Oh, this "Bracelet" looks cool.
デザインが馴染みやすいから普段使いしやすそうだし、ライオンの加護もついてるんだー
The design is easy to match, so it seems easy to wear daily, plus it comes with a lion's blessing.
これをつけてたらキミもライオンになれるかも……なーんと
If you wear this, maybe you can become a lion too... Just kidding!
ふふ、これ、かわいいな。ヘルメットをかぶってる
Hehe, this is cute. It's wearing a helmet.
『SSRBぬいぐるみキーホルダー』……つけてるだけですっごく楽しい気分になれそう
"SSRB Plush Keychain"... Just carrying it around feels like it'll boost your mood.
手のひらサイズのちょうどいい大きさだからバックパックにぶら下げてもいいし、ベルトにつけるのもとかもありかな
It's just the right palm-sized dimension, so hanging it on a backpack or clipping it to a belt would work great too.
これも買い候補っと
Adding this to my buy list too.
どうしよう、全部欲しい……
What should I do? I want all of them...
どれにするか迷う……
I can't decide which one to get...
え、これを全部まとめたセットもあるんだ？
Huh, there's a set that bundles all of these together?
しかもそれだと、収納袋の絵を描いているトマリ先生の描き下ろしのポストカードと直筆サイン、箔押しメッセージ……が特典でついてくるのか……
Plus with that set, it comes with a newly drawn postcard by Tomari-sensei—who drew the storage bag art—along with a handwritten signature and a foil-stamped message as a bonus gift?
……セットでください
...I'll take the set, please.
……やっとわかった気がする
...I feel like I finally understand.
AZKi、ミオ、わため……
AZKi, Mio, Watame...
ラオーラ...
Raora...
アキロゼ...
Akirose...
リオナ...
Riona...
かなた...
Kanata...
そしてこの舞台に向けて声援を送ってくれていたたくさんのみんな...
And everyone who sent their cheers toward this stage...
みんなから受け取ったたくさんのもの... そこに込められた想い。
Everything I received from everyone... and the feelings put into them.
それらが集まって... 『オンガク』になる。
When all of those gather... they become "music."
――新しいあたしが生まれたんだ。
—A new me is born.
うん、キミならそう言ってくれると思った。
Yeah, I knew you'd say that.
そんなキミにボクから... ボクたちから... 最後に「曲」を贈るよ。
To you, from me... from us... we give you one last "song."
今日という素敵な日の最後を飾る... 新しい獅白ぼたんの誕生を祝う、世界でひとつだけの「曲」。
Celebrating the birth of the new Shishiro Botan to top off this wonderful day, a one-of-a-kind "song" in the world.
今のキミなら歌えるはず。
The current you should be able to sing it.
「音楽」を――取り戻せるはずだから。
Because you should be able to... reclaim "music."
がおってこ！
[Title: Gaotteko!]
がおってこ！ がおってこ！ がおってこ！ がおってこ！
Let's roar! Let's roar! Let's roar! Let's roar!
15分早起きした
I woke up 15 minutes early,
奇跡的な起床記録
a miraculous waking record.
珍しい誇らしい朝
A rare, proud morning,
誰のせいでしょうか？
I wonder whose fault it is?
きみのがおが聴こえると 気がするだけかもしれないけど
When I hear your roar, even if it might just be my imagination,
無敵になる気がして
I feel invincible,
走って 走って 走れんだ
and I can run, run, run!
Shine on! どこって迷っちゃっても
(Shine on!) Even if I get lost asking "Where?"
Ride on! 合図は遠くの声
(Ride on!) The signal is a voice from afar!
Vibe on! 迎えに行くよ We're Lions!!
(Vibe on!) I'll come to get you! We're Lions!!
Shine on! きみがいる世界が
(Shine on!) The world you're in
Ride on! 輝く合言葉
(Ride on!) is our shining password!
がおっていいヤツみんなで
Together with everyone who roars,
Everybody, say 1-2-3!!
がおってこ がおってこ
Let's roar! Let's roar!
ひとりじゃないって魔法をかけたら
Once we cast a spell saying "You're not alone,"
がおってこ がおってこ
let's roar! Let's roar!
不安にだって一緒に吠えて
We'll even roar at our anxieties together!
がおってこ がおってこ
Let's roar! Let's roar!
笑顔でバフかけちゃえるから
'Cause we can buff each other with smiles!
がおってこ がおってこ
Let's roar! Let's roar!
ここがそう 私達の最高
Right here, this is our absolute best!
Rawr rawr!! Yeah! Rawr rawr!! Yeah!
一日一獅子 Motivation
One lion a day for motivation!
低めのやる気ががおで上昇
Low motivation rises with a roar!
Join us my peeps! 百獣で優勝
Join us my peeps! Winning as king of beasts!
だからがおっていきましょう
So let's all roar together!
靴擦れした右足が
The blister on my right foot
今日のやる気を持ってった
took away my motivation for today.
椅子の角っこが小指も
The corner of a chair also
ついでにしばいてくれた
smashed my pinky toe for good measure.
きみのがおが聴こえると
But when I hear your roar,
そんな日もちょっとやさしくなる
even days like that become a little kinder.
おすそわけしたくて
Wanting to share this feeling,
踊って 踊って 踊ってんだ
I dance, dance, and dance!
がおってこ がおってこ
Let's roar! Let's roar!
ジャンプするなら今しかないし
If we're gonna jump, there's no time like now,
がおってこ がおってこ
so let's roar! Let's roar!
高いトコ目指しちゃおうよ Let's go!
Let's aim for higher places, let's go!
Shine on! “この一瞬がプレゼント”
(Shine on!) "This moment is a gift"
Ride on! なんて真顔じゃ言えない
(Ride on!) is something I can't say with a straight face!
Vibe on! だから吠えちゃうな We're Lions!!
(Vibe on!) So I'll just roar it out! We're Lions!!
Shine on! きみがいる毎日が
(Shine on!) Every day that you're in
Ride on! 歌う合言葉
(Ride on!) is a singing password!
がおっていいヤツみんなで
Together with everyone who roars,
Everybody, say 1-2-3!!
がおってこ がおってこ
Let's roar! Let's roar!
小声でも Say ちゃんと聴こえてる
Even if it's a whisper, say it, I can hear you clearly!
がおってこ がおってこ
Let's roar! Let's roar!
じゃあ叫んだら未来に届く!?
So if we shout, will it reach the future!?
がおってこ がおってこ
Let's roar! Let's roar!
みんなでなら 446dB
Together we can reach 446 dB!
がおってこ がおってこ
Let's roar! Let's roar!
ここがそう 私達の最高
Right here, this is our absolute best!
Rawr rawr!! Yeah! Rawr rawr!! Yeah!
言葉にすると真っ直ぐすぎて
Putting it into words feels too straightforward,
くすぐったい胸の奥が だから!
it tickles deep inside my chest, so...
がおってこ がおってこ
Let's roar! Let's roar!
「ありがとう」のかわりを
Instead of saying "Thank you,"
がおってこ がおってこ
let's roar! Let's roar!
ここがそう 私達の最高
Right here, this is our absolute best!
これは... あたしが見てる夢？
Is this... a dream I'm having?
それとも...
Or is it...
それとも「ライブ」をしてるあたしの方が 今のあたしが見てる...夢？
Or is the "me" performing in the live concert... actually a dream the current me is seeing?
胡蝶の夢って知ってる？
Do you know the story of the Butterfly's Dream?
キミの言う通り この世界はもしかしたら もう一人のキミが見ている夢なのかもしれないし
Just as you said, this world might be a dream that another version of you is dreaming,
もしかしたらさっきまでキミが見ていた「ライブ」こそが この世界のキミが見ている夢かもしれない
or perhaps the "live concert" you were watching until just now is the dream that the "you" in this world is seeing.
もしかしたらいつか訪れる未来なのかもしれないし
Maybe it's a future that will come true someday,
観測された違う世界線を 垣間見ているだけなのかもしれない
or maybe you're just catching a glimpse of a different observed worldline.
世界は不確定なんだよ
The world is uncertain, you know.
「音楽」は そんなたくさんの世界を繋ぐ糸みたいなもの
"Music" is like a thread that connects all those many worlds.
数え切れないほど存在する可能性の中 それでも「音楽」だけはいつだってそこにあるものなの
Among the countless possibilities that exist, music is the one thing that will always be there.
うちたちが ぼたんのことを想う気持ちもね
And so is the way we all feel about you, Botan.
わため どこにいてもぼたんちゃんのこと大好きだよぉ
Watame loves you no matter where I am, Botan-chan!
ぼたん先輩の絵 また描きたいなー！
I want to draw pictures of Botan-senpai again!
ふふ ししろーと同じ時間をのんびり過ごすの アキロゼはすごーく好きかなー
Hehe, AkiRose really loves spending relaxing time together with Shishiro~
ぼたん先輩 いつかは私と一緒にまた歌ってほしいです！でもその前に...
Botan-senpai, I want to sing with you again someday! But before that...
せーの！
One, two, three...
誕生日おめでとう！
Happy Birthday!
みんな...
Everyone...
...ありがとう
...Thank you.
みんなの気持ち 送ってくれたお祝いの言葉... 確かに受け取ったよ
Everyone's feelings, the celebratory words you sent... I've truly received them all.
すごく... すごく嬉しい
I'm so... so happy.
今ならきっと 前だけを見て走っていられる...
Now, I feel like I can keep running forward looking only ahead...
これからも新しい世界に まだ見たことのないたくさんの可能性に 挑戦することができる！
From now on too, I can take on new worlds and so many unseen possibilities!
だってここが... あたしたちの最高だから！
Because this place... is our absolute best!
だから この先も一緒に行こう！
So let's go forward together beyond this!
次に生まれるのがどんな世界でも！
No matter what world I am born into next!
ーみんなのこと 本当に 本当に大好きだよ！
I love everyone so, so very much!
(次にあたしが生まれるのは どこなんだろう)
(Where will I be born next, I wonder?)
(でもそれがどこでも大丈夫)
(But wherever that may be, it'll be okay.)
(さよならはいわない)
(I won't say goodbye.)
(きっとあたしはこの幸せな物語を胸に どこまでだって飛べるはずだから)
(Because with this happy story in my heart, I know I can fly anywhere.)
(ーそこに「音楽」と みんなからもらった温かくてやさしい想いがあれば！)
(As long as there's "music" and the warm, gentle feelings I received from everyone!)
次の世界で また会おう...！
Let's meet again in the next world...!
きみがいる世界で...！
In the world where you are...!
新しい世界に旅立つ？
Journey to a new world?
SHISHIRO BOTAN BIRTHDAY 3D LIVE MUST RELIVE